Inventory of the Polish Grey Samaritans records
Hoover Institution Archives
Polish Grey Samaritans records
1918-1965
57026
Polish Grey Samaritans.
3 manuscript boxes (1.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives. Stanford, California 94305-6010
Memoirs, reports, correspondence, printed matter, photographs, and memorabilia, relating to relief activities carried out in Poland at the end of World War I, and to conditions in Poland at that time. Includes memoirs by Martha Gedgowd and Amy Pryor Tapping, members of the Polish Grey Samaritans.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1957.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
Organization of Polish-American women relief workers.
Scope and Content of Collection
Memoirs, reports, correspondence, printed matter, photographs, and memorabilia, relating to relief activities carried out in Poland at the end of World War I, and to conditions in Poland at that time. Includes memoirs by Martha Gedgowd and Amy Pryor Tapping, members of the Polish Grey Samaritans.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
International relief.; Polish Americans.; World War, 1914-1918--Civilian relief.; World War, 1914-1918--Poland.; Poland--Economic conditions 1918-1945.; Poland--Social conditions.; Gedgowd, Martha.; Tapping, Amy Pryor.
Collection Contents
- "Preparation for Polish Grey's in USA,", 1918-1919 (Folder 1: 1)
- Amy Tapping documents and photos of Grey Ladies, circa 1919 (Folder 1: 2)
- First trip correspondence and pamphlets, circa 1920 (Folder 1: 3)
- Background materials and booklist, circa 1920 (Folder 1: 4)
  Includes "The Polish Grey Samaritans - An Adventure in Americanization"
- "The First American Peace Corps,", May, 1920 (Folder 1: 5)
  The Polish Greys Become Acquainted with the American Relief Administration (ARA). The Polish Greys Become Permanent Members of the A.R.A
- Poland food distribution correspondence, relief work reports, and maps, September 1920 (Folder 1: 6)
- Polish G.S. General, circa 1920, 1934, 1944, 1957 (Folder 1: 7)
  Newspaper clippings, personal accounts, letters; From Poland to Africa
- "How the Polish Grey Samaritains Met the Bolshevik Advance into Poland" manuscript, July, 1922 (Folder 1: 8)
- Amy Tapping correspondence, 1963-1964 (Folder 1: 9)
- Polish Grey Ladies, Amy Tapping correspondence, 1964-1965 (Folder 1: 10)
- Luncheon in Honor of the Polish Grey Samaritans Unit of the Y.W.C.A, invitation and correspondence, 15 August 1921 (Folder 1: 11)
- Polish Grey Samaritans, expenses and financial reports, 1923 (Folder 1: 12)
- Clothing distributions, December 1919 (Folder 1: 13)
- Kopeck's illness payment, circa 1922 (Folder 1: 14)
- Cablegrams, circa 1922 (Folder 1: 15)
- Amy Tapping, official documents, 1919-1922 (Folder 2: 1)
- Bulletins and correspondence providing accounts of individual Grey Samaritans members and their role in Poland, circa 1922 (Folder 2: 2)
- Correspondence, travel arrangements, and reports, 1920-1925 (Folder 2: 3)
- Martha Gedgowd's account of her experiences in Poland, 1919-1923 (Folder 2: 4)
- Reports and experiences of Polish Grey Samaritans, circa 1920 (Folder 2: 5-6)
  Includes Felicia Krotaviez and Mary Andrezsy, among others
- Correspondence, reports, experiences, circa 1921 (Folder 2: 7)
- "The Story of the Polish Grey Samaritans,", August 1920 - July 1922 (Folder 2: 8)
  Includes description of their last two years in Poland
- Notebook with personal accounts of the Polish Grey Samaritans, Monitor Polish Daily blank notebook, 11 November 1941 (Folder 3: 1-2)
- "The Problem of Cieszyn Silesia: Facts and Documents,", October 1943 (Folder 3: 3)
- Accounts notebook, 2 October 1920 (Folder 3: 4)
- "American Relief Administration European Children's Fund Mission to Poland," publication including statistics, goals, and accomplishments, 1919-1922 (Folder 3: 5)
- Martha Graczyk notebook and reports, undated (Folder 3: 6)
- Martha Graczyk notebook and reports (contd.), undated (Folder 4: 1)
- Emily Graves, photographs and descriptions of Warsaw, 1920-1922 (Folder 4: 2)
- Photographs, general, undated (Folder 4: 3)
- Photographs and postcards of soldiers, and the Polish Grey Samaritans Lodge, 1919-1921 (Folder 4: 4)
- Photographs of groups, ships, the Statue of Liberty, and reunions, and correspondence from Martha Graczyk, circa 1919, 1933 (Folder 4: 5)
- Photographs of a YMCA school room, undated (Folder 4: 6)
- Photograph albums, undated (Box 5)
  - Album cover, undated (Folder 5: 1)
  - Loose photographs from album, undated (Folder 5: 2)
  - Daily activities in Germany and France, undated (Folder 5: 3)
  - Daily activities in Warsaw, circa 1919 (Folder 5: 4)
  - A.R.A children's food kitchen and miscellaneous, undated (Folder 5: 5)
  - Harvest, prisoners, miscellany, undated (Folder 5: 6)
  - Polish villages, undated (Folder 5: 7)
  - Anna Kopec, Helen Mielcarrer, and miscellany, undated (Folder 5: 8)